{"tossups": [{"question": "This man was forced to begin his most famous campaign after his compatriots launched a drunken raid on settlements by the Salmon River. This leader was able to escape the clutches of Samuel Sturgis at the Battle of Canyon Creek, even though he was betrayed by the Crow tribe. After Oliver Howard captured this man at the Battle of Bear Paw Mountain, this leader said that he \u201cwill fight no more forever.\u201d For ten points, name this chief of the Nez Perce who attempted to lead his tribe to Canada.", "answer": "Chief<b> Joseph</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This treaty was the target of the bull<em> Zelo Domus Dei</em>, in which Pope Innocent X declared it \u201cempty of meaning and effect for all time.\u201d This treaty guaranteed free navigation on the Rhine and reaffirmed the principle of<em> cuius regio, eius religio</em> laid out in the Peace of Augsburg. The Eighty Years\u2019 War was ended as a result of this treaty, which combined negotiations at Osnabruck and Munster. For ten points, name this peace treaty that ended the Thirty Years War.", "answer": "Peace of<b> Westphalia</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This philosopher rejected that humans have a real notion of self in formulating his \u201cbundle theory.\u201dThis thinker, who wrote a massively successful<em> History of England</em>, originated a problem sometimes called his \u201cguillotine,\u201d the Is-Ought problem. This author of \u201cOf Miracles\u201d divided statements into \u201crelations of ideas\u201d and \u201cmatters of fact.\u201d A \u201cmissing shade of blue\u201d was imagined by, for ten points, what Scottish philosopher who wrote<em> An Enquiry Concerning Human Understanding</em>?", "answer": "David<b> Hume</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s most famous endeavor was thwarted by Executive Order 1111, which placed his officers under federal control. After this man refused to listen to Attorney General Nicholas Katzenbach, he was confronted by Henry Graham when John F. Kennedy called up the National Guard. This man opposed James Hood and Vivian Malone at the Foster Auditorium after declaring his support for \u201csegregation forever.\u201d For ten points, name this governor of Alabama who made the \u201cstand in the schoolhouse door\u201din 1963.", "answer": "George<b> Wallace</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This piece in C minor, which opens with a dominant seventh chord followed by loud descending runs of sixteenth notes, was dedicated to \u201chis friend Franz Liszt.\u201d The event that inspired this work caused its composer to lament \u201cAll this has caused me much pain. Who could have forseen it?\u201d; that event, the failing of the 1831 November Uprising, crushed hopes for freedom in its composer\u2019s native Poland. For ten points, name this work for solo piano, an etude [ay-tood] by Frederic Chopin [sho-pan].", "answer": "<b> Revolutionary</b> Etude (or<b> Etude on the Bombardment of Warsaw</b>; accept<b> Etude Opus 10, Number 12</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "At the 1205 Battle of Adrianople, this man led a force that joined Baldwin the I of the Latin Empire to fight Tsar Kaloyan of the Bulgars. Michael Comnenus may have ordered the blinding of this man, and his daughter Anna married the king of Serbia, Stefan Nemanjic. This man, who introduced the silver grosso as currency in Venice, joined crusaders at the St. Mark\u2019s Basilica. Isaac II was replaced with Alexius Angelus in the Fourth Crusade by, for ten points, what blind Doge of Venice?", "answer": "Enrico<b> Dandolo</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In this city, the Fortaleza do Monte overlooks the remains of a church whose facade was constructed by Japanese Christians under Carlo Spinola. Following a Dutch East India Company attack on this city in 1622, the Guia Fortress was built. The Bridge of Friendship is one of three bridges connecting parts of this city, where reclamation projects connected the islands of Coloane and Taipa. For ten points, name this special administrative region in the Pearl River Delta alongside Hong Kong, a city that was under Portuguese control until 1999.", "answer": "<b> Macau</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "A cheese spread made by this civilization was known as Moretum. This civilization built the Barbegal complex to as a watermill to process grain, and they used the Burdigala region to grow wine grapes. Garum was a fish sauce created by this civilization, whose Frumentarii secret service collected wheat. For ten points, name this ancient civilization whose agricultural writings include works by Cato the Elder.", "answer": "ancient<b> Rome</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man produced two paintings from the view of Westminster and Waterloo Bridge to offer differing perspectives on the 1834 burning of the houses of Parliament. This man depicted a 98-gun ship being towed to be broken up in his<em> Fighting Temeraire</em>. Another painting by this artist is set on the Maidenhead Bridge and seemingly shows a hare running from a train. For ten points, name this British artist of<em> Rain,</em> <em>Steam, and Speed</em>.", "answer": "Joseph Mallord William \u201cJ.M.W.\u201d<b> Turner</b> BONUS:<em> The Fighting Temeraire</em> was one of the last remaining ships to have fought in this 1805 battle, where she rammed the<em> Redoutable</em>. ANSWER: Battle of<b> Trafalgar</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Giangiacomo Feltrinelli was the first to publish this author\u2019s most famous work after it was smuggled out of its native country. The CIA declassified dozens of documents about its role in supporting that work by this author, which begins with the funeral of the title character\u2019s mother Marya and is interspersed with scenes between the title character and Lara Antipov. This man claimed that leaving Russia would be \u201ctantamount to death\u201d as one of his reasons for declining the 1958 Nobel Prize in Literature. For ten points, name this Russian author of<em> Dr. Zhivago</em>.", "answer": "Boris<b> Pasternak</b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "This monarch was crowned under the statute Titulus Regius after ordering the arrest of Earl Rivers. This ruler claimed that his predecessor\u2019s marriage to Elizabeth Woodville was illegitimate and took the throne after supposedly ordering James Tyrell to murder the Princes in the Tower. This man was slain at the Battle of Bosworth Field, making him the final Plantagenet ruler. For ten points, name this king from the House of York during the War of the Roses.", "answer": "<b> Richard III</b> (prompt on Richard)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Forty seven years before this case,<em> Weeks v. U.S.</em> dealt with the same rule, but only at the federal level. The defendant of this case worked under Shon Birns, a gambling kingpin. The \u201cFruit of the Poisonous Tree\u201d doctrine was added to the Exclusionary rule that this decision applied to the states. The defendant argued that paraphernalia and books were taken without probable cause in, for ten points, what Fourth Amendment case that outlawed evidence taken from \u201cunreasonable search and seizures?\u201d", "answer": "<b> Mapp</b> v. Ohio BONUS:<em> Mapp v Ohio</em> applied the Fourth Amendment to the states in a process that involves the 14th Amendment and is known by this term. ANSWER: (selective)<b> incorporation</b> (accept word forms)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>During this war, the Volunteer Army was forced to take the Ice March towards the Kuban region. Two rival governments formed during this war at Omsk and Samara. The (+) Czechoslovak Legion revolted and controlled most of a railway during this war; another major revolt in this war was launched by sailors at (*)</b> Kronstadt who were angry at the policies of wartime communism implemented by Leon Trotsky. For ten points, name this war between the Red and White Armies, ending in a Bolshevik triumph.", "answer": "<b> Russian Civil</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>A 1993 attack on this organization\u2019s headquarters was carried out by Pakistani terrorist Mir Qazi. In a 2003 scandal, Robert Novak revealed that Valerie Plame worked for</b> <b>this organization. Following revelations of his (+)</b> <b>affair with Paula Broadwell, David</b> <b>Petraeus stepped down as head of this organization, which helped plan an assassination in (*) </b> Abbottabad, Pakistan carried out by Seal Team Six. The assassination of Osama bin Laden was masterminded by, for ten points, what American agency that engages in covert action overseas?", "answer": "<b> C</b>entral<b> I</b>ntelligence<b> A</b>gency", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>The lands of these people were surveyed by Henry Bulwer, who tried to convince Bartle Frere not to begin a series of annexations. Lord Chelmsford gave these people an ultimatum</b> <b>in order to force them to declare war, a conflict that ended when (+)</b> <b>Ulundi was burned</b> <b>Ulundi was burned</b> <b>and king Cetshwayo was sent into exile. These people fought the battles of (*)</b> <b>and king Cetshwayo was sent into exile. These people fought the battles of (*)</b> Isandlwana and Rorke\u2019s Drift against British forces. For ten points, name this South African ethnic group that was once led by Shaka.", "answer": "<b> Zulu</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>The longest single story in the Quran re-tells the life of this prophet. The Biblical book named for this prophet is read as haftarah on the afternoon of Yom Kippur. This man, who prophecies to a group of people who \u201ccould not tell their right hand from their left,\u201dgets (+) belligerent after a fast-growing gourd-vine he was using for shade gets eaten by a worm. This prophet tried to (*) </b> sail to Tarshish to avoid prophesying doom to Nineveh as he was commanded. For ten points, name this Biblical prophet who is swallowed by a huge fish.", "answer": "<b> Jonah</b> (or<b> Jonas</b>; or<b> Yunus</b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b>This location inspired a similar development in Toa Baja, Puerto Rico that was divided into eight sections and numerous sub-sections. Zip code 11756 was given to this location,</b> <b>where documents required that \u201cany person other than a member of the (+)</b> <b>Caucasian</b> <b>race\u201d could not buy. This location in Nassau County consisted of units that could be (*) </b>financed with 30-year mortgages that required no down payment. At one point, a house was built every 16 minutes in, for ten points, what \u201cmass-produced\u201d suburb in 1950s New York?", "answer": "<b> Levittown</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This event inspired most of the album</b><em><b> The Rising</b></em><b> by Bruce Springsteen, including its song \u201cMy City of Ruins.\u201d Clear Channel Communications released a memo suggesting that\u201cImagine\u201d by John Lennon, every song by Rage Against the Machine, and over 100 other</b> <b>songs (+)</b> <b>not be played on the radio in the wake of this event. Paul McCartney\u2019s single</b> <b>not be played on the radio in the wake of this event. Paul McCartney\u2019s single</b> <b>\u201cFreedom\u201d was written after he witnessed this event from the (*)</b> <b>\u201cFreedom\u201d was written after he witnessed this event from the (*)</b> tarmac of JFK airport in Queens. For ten points, name this terrorist attack that was memorialized by a benefit concert in New York in October 2001.", "answer": "<b> September 11</b>th, 2001 attacks (accept<b> 9/11</b> attacks; accept<b> 2001 World Trade Center attack</b>s and any other specific aspect of the 9/11 attacks; prompt on \u201cWorld Trade Center attack;\u201d do not accept or prompt \u201cWorld Trade Center bombing\u201d)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>This man ended the revolt of the Obotrites at the battle of Recknitz and secured power after facing a rebellion from Liudolf and Conrad the Red. The creation of the Gero Codex and a scriptorium at Quedlinburg led scholars to name a (+) \u201cRenaissance\u201d after this man. This man was crowned in 962 by Pope John XII, seven years after a victory over Bulcsu ended (*)</b> Magyar raids into Western Europe. For ten points, identify this \u201cGreat\u201d German Holy Roman Emperor who was victorious at Lechfeld.", "answer": "<b> Otto the Great</b> (accept<b> Otto I</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>A signatory of the Declaration of Independence from this state named John Witherspoon helped shift the emphasis of one of its universities away from clerical training. A governor</b> <b>of this colony who believed the Stamp Act was justified was an (+)</b> <b>illegitimate son of</b> <b>Benjamin Franklin named William. Known as the Crossroads of the Revolution, this state is home to a (*)</b> university attended by James Madison and Aaron Burr; that university shares its name with a nearby 1777 battle. For ten points, name this home state of Princeton University.", "answer": "<b> New Jersey</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker!", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This project was the subject of the Mallarino-Bidlack treaty, which granted the</b> <b>right to launch a military intervention. The Chagres River was dammed as part of</b> <b>this project. (+) Scotland attempted this project through the Darien Scheme, which</b> <b>was thwarted by malaria. The (*)</b> Carter-Torrijos treaties transferred control of this project, which was designed around the artificial Gatun Lake. For ten points, name this Central American waterway linking the Atlantic to the Pacific.", "answer": "<b> Panama Canal</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}